Finding Aid for Lawrence A. Rubin papers, 1934-2011
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Lawrence A. Rubin papers 1934-2011
Rubin, Lawrence A., 1912-
2 linear feet
852168 Aa 2
Writer, head of advertising agency, long-time executive director of the Mackinac Bridge Authority; correspondence, files relating to political advertising work in the 1930s, manuscripts of short stories and other writings, subject files relating to interests and activities.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection came first from Lawrence A. Rubin (donor no. 4806 ) in 1969; in 2011 David J. Rubin (donor no. 10586 ) donated additional materials.
Additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Lawrence A. Rubin was born December 7, 1912 in Chelsea, Massachusetts. He moved with his family to Detroit, Michigan sometime around 1927-28. He went to the University of Michigan in 1930, graduating with an A.B. degree in 1934. Upon graduation, Rubin open his own advertising agency. In 1936, he served as radio director for Frank Murphy's winning campaign for governor; and following, in April 1937 he accepted the position of assistant director of the Public Relations Division of the Michigan State Highway Department where he served under Murray D. Van Wagoner and G. Donald Kennedy. Much of his work here was political in nature, writing copy used in Van Wagoner's re-election campaign for highway commission and his later successful campaign for governor in 1940. Rubin's other responsibilities were to publicize the work of the Highway Department.
After Pearl Harbor, from December 1941 to May 1942, Rubin was given temporary release to perform public relations duties for the Detroit Ordnance District of the War Department. On May 6, 1942, he was inducted into the Army. Throughout his career, Rubin wrote short stories, poetry, personal and historical essays. Some of his energy after the war went into his effort to become a writer. To develop his skills, from 1946 to 1947 he attended the Magazine Institute where he learned the skills of writing fiction. In 1947 he was appointed executive director of the Michigan Good Roads Federation where with others he participated in a highway needs study that eventually led to the passage in 1951 of important highway legislation. He served with the Federation until 1952.
In 1950, Rubin moved to Michigan's Upper Peninsula when he was appointed executive secretary of the Mackinac Bridge Authority where he would remain until his retirement in 1983. Rubin figured importantly in the financing and construction of the bridge. After its opening in 1957, Rubin continued to supervise the operation and maintenance of the Bridge. Always a promoter of the Bridge and the importance of the Upper Peninsula as a tourist destination, Rubin also served as president of the Upper Peninsula Travel and Recreation Association and he was selected by Governor Milliken as Ambassador of Michigan Tourism. From 1954 to 1960, he also served as secretary-treasurer of the International Bridge Authority where bonds were sold to obtain funds for a bridge between the United States and Canada at Sault Ste. Marie.
Rubin remained active in his retirement writing a history of the Mackinac Bridge, giving speeches and talks, and continuing as spokesperson for the Upper Peninsula. He died May 11, 2010.
The Lawrence A. Rubin papers document phases in the life of this author and public servant. A small collection of papers relating to his public relations work for Democratic candidates for governor in 1936 and 1940 (Frank Murphy and Murray D. Van Wagoner) was received in 1969. Additional papers came from David Rubin following his father's passing in 2010. Further additions are expected.
The collection is generally arranged chronologically with some periods in Rubin's career being more fully documented than others. There are some files relating to his public relations work for the Michigan State Highway Department prior to his World War II service. There is substantially less for his activities with the Mackinac Bridge Authority. Of importance here are copies of some of the financial instruments detailing the funding of the Bridge. Throughout his life Rubin was a writer of short stories and of journal articles about the building of the Bridge, his wartime experiences, and his affection for Michigan's Upper Peninsula. Many of these stories were written under the pseudonym of Massie Davis. These manuscripts and drafts are important because they show that Rubin always considered writing to be a part of his life.
Subjects:
Elections--Michigan--1936.; Mackinac Bridge Authority (Mich.); Mackinac Bridge (Mich.); Michigan--Politics and government--1837-1950.; Michigan--Politics and government--1929-1938.; Michigan. State Highway Dept.; Murphy, Frank, 1890-1949.; Upper Peninsula (Mich.); Van Wagoner, Murray Delos, 1898-
- Politics and Government Service (pre-1950 career)
  - Public relations work 1934-1937 (Box 1)
  - Frank Murphy campaign for governor 1936
    - Correspondence, telegrams, text of FM speeches (Box 1)
    - Clippings and related material (Box 1)
    - Collected material (including FM biography) (Box 1)
  - Murray D. Van Wagoner campaign for State Highway Commissioner 1937 (Box 1)
  - Murray D. Van Wagoner campaign for governor 1940
    - Budgets and schedules (Box 1)
    - Campaign literature (Box 1)
    - Contracts with radio stations and related (Box 1)
    - Foreign language radio programs (Box 1)
    - General correspondence (Box 1)
    - Headquarters correspondence (Box 1)
    - Itineraries (Box 1)
    - Newspaper rates (Box 1)
    - Radio station rates (Box 1)
  - Michigan State Highway Department
    - General: include texts of Van Wagoner and others who spoke on radio about highway issues (Box 1)
    - Radio scripts 1939-1940 (Box 1)
  - World War II service
    - Miscellaneous, prior to May 1942 induction (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous, after induction (Box 1)
    - Writings (Box 1)
      (brief stories probably while in the service)
  - Magazine Institute 1946-1947 (Box 1)
- Post-1950 activities
  - Mackinac Bridge Authority
    - Financial re revenue bonds 1953 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous (include some snapshots of the bridge with Rubin) (Box 1)
    - Personnel issues (general) (Box 1)
    - Lawrence Rubin vs. Michigan State Highway Dept. and Michigan Civil Service Commission (regarding retirement credits) 1959-1960 (Box 1)
    - Various reports: engineering, traffic and revenues, general 1951, 1953 (Box 1)
  - Father Marquette Memorial Dedication 1976 (Box 1)
    (include poem about Marquette by LAR)
  - International Bridge Authority 1954, 1960 (Box 1)
  - Hospital Millage Campaign Book 1990 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Outdoor Writers Association 1982 (Box 1)
  - Mackinac Manor (St. Ignace apartment house complex) 1976 (Box 1)
    (LAR was the developer)
- Personal: Correspondence, Writings, Speeches, Financial
  - Correspondence 1935-2003, undated
    - Undated (Box 2)
    - 1935-1937 (Box 2)
    - 1940-1941 (Box 2)
    - 1942-1972 (Box 2)
    - 1976-1977 (Box 2)
    - 1979 (Box 2)
    - 1980-1981 (Box 2)
    - 1982 (Box 2)
    - 1983 (Box 2)
    - 1986 (Box 2)
    - 1987 (Box 2)
    - 1988 (Box 2)
    - 1989 (Box 2)
    - 1990 (Box 2)
    - 1991 (Box 2)
    - 1992-1995 (Box 2)
    - 1996 (Box 2)
    - 1997 (Box 2)
    - 1998 (Box 2)
    - 1999 (Box 2)
    - 2000 (Box 2)
    - 2001 (Box 2)
    - 2002 (Box 2)
    - 2003 (Box 2)
    - Letters from his son David (Box 2)
  - Writings
    - Stories written under the pseudonym of Massie Davis and submitted as assignments to the Magazine Institute or for publication to various magazines 1946-1947 (Box 2)
    - Essay circa 1951-1952 entitled "How to Plan and Pay for the Adequate Highways We Need" submitted to Board of Judges of the General Motors Better Highways Awards contest (Box 2)
    - Text of dramatic program based on the experiences of a special agent, U.S. Army Counter Intelligence Corps (Box 2)
    - Short story: "Two Points for Dolly" 1952 (Box 2)
    - Untitled short story with espionage theme (Box 2)
    - Short stories with accompanying rejection slips from various magazines 1946-1949 (Box 2)
  - Speeches 1961-2001 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Photographs (Box 2)